)r. M. Usman Magbool **Bhutta**

Room 205, Academic Building 1, CUHK, Hong Kong.

□ (+852) 609-44-786 | wsmanmaqbool@outlook.com | # usmanmaqbool.github.io | □ UsmanMaqbool | □ usmanmaqbool

"Roboticist + Entrepreneur"

Summary.

With the rise of autonomous systems, being a researcher and entrepreneur, my research direction is their deployment to the real world. For any autonomous mode of the robot, a 3D map is essential to navigate and operate at any place. I work to tackle the problems related to scale difference and loop closures for large scale 3D mapping. I've 7+ years of experience specializing in robotics R&D and project management. I previously owned an IT company, and I've been part of several startups since 2011. My full profile can view here (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

Work Experience

Research (Computer Vision Technologies and Robotics System)

C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), Department of Mechanical and Automation Engineering

CUHK, Hong Kong.

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

May. 2021 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Darwin Lau, Director of C3 Robotics Laboratory (C3RL), The Chinese University of Hong Kong CUHK, Hong Kong...
- Research in place recognition, AR/VR and inspection robotics for construction I'm working on several projects here

Place Recognition: Working on the light-weight representation of images and making better use of previously trained models.

AR/VR: Research in AR/VR Platform design, multi-agent mixed reality, assistive prosthetics for the handicapped persons, teleoperated robots, human-robot interaction.

Inspection: Deep learning based research for the robotic presurface inspection for the construction.

Multi-agent collaboration: For indoor vegetation and painting robotics application.

Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics Institute

HKUST, HK

PhD

Sep 2016 - Feb 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- **Research Contributions as First Author**

Place Recognition: Our work makes a leap towards hierarchical deep learning-based place recognition for multiagent SLAM systems. We introduce a probabilistic layer to constrain the local representation along with the global representation of images. The global description of the pre-trained model and the local consistency introduced in our work enables the system to yield good performance at large-scale.

Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work is accepted for publication in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF= 11+)...

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

Automation (Inspection): For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL)

ETH Zürich, Switzerland.

Academic Guest

MPhil Candidate

Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Department of Electronics

OAU, Pakistan

M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

Industry and Entrepreneurship

Lisee Technology Corporation Limited

COO Jan 2018 - Jan 2021

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 - May 20).

- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 - May 19).

Friends Corporate Technologies

Islamabad, PK

Central HK

CEO Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

Federal Government of Pakistan

Islamabad, PK

Scientific Officer

May 2012 - Feb 2013

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing

Server4Sale, LLC Islamabad, PK

PHP Developer Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

Academic

Department of Computer Science BZU-Sahiwal, Pakistan

Lecturer (Visiting)

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

Department of Physics GPGC Sahiwal, Pakistan

CTI Oct. 2015 - May. 2016

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

Department of Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Instructer

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Education

Ph.D. in Robotics and AI at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

HKUST, Hong Kong

Department of Electronic & Computer Engineering, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

Sep. 2016 - Feb. 2021

Thesis: "Towards A Swift Multiagent SLAM System For Large-scale Robotics Applications", June 17, 2021

• PhD Supervisor: **Prof Ming Liu**, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (**RAM-LAB**)

- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: **Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma**, Senior Researcher at ASL, **ETH Zürich**, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry. Hand on experience on RGB-D 3D recontruction, Multi-view stereo, python and C++ development experience, multi-threaded coding.3D mesh registration, paraview and parameterizations. Moreover, I've deep understanding of data structures and algorithms. Experience with software development on Linux open-source stack. Calculus, linear algebra and geometry related courses have been taken.

M.Phil. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research: Signal and Image Processing
- Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• 2nd position in batch

· Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics

BZU, Pakistan

Bahauddin Zakariya University, Multan Pakistan

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

Grade: 1st Division

Presentation

CUHK, Hong Kong

Posters Presentation Jul. 2021

- · 'Mixed Reality in Hands-On Learning of Robotics' by Xinyan Zhao, Sabrina Lam, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.
- 'Online Robotics Laboratory Framework for Interactive and Group Hands-On Learning' by Ken Hui, Ken Kwok, M. Usman M. Bhutta, Darwin Lau and Jimmy Lee.

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

Presentor as author

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jan. 2019

• Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

Presentor as author

Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

CityU, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jul. 2018

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as participent

May 2018

Dec. 2017

HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as Entrepreneur

• Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

Presenter as author.

Nov. 2017

• Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

Honors & Awards

July, 20	21 Educational Technology Innovation: Gold Award , The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK	CUHK, Hong Kong
July, 20	21 Pedagogical Innovation: Silver Award , The Teaching and Learning Innovation Expo, CUHK	CUHK, Hong Kong
July, 20	Best Student Paper Finalist Award, IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems	Tianjin, China
May, 20	18 Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Nov, 20	17 Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
May, 20	17 Completion Award, The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Dec, 20	16 Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
Nov, 20	16 Completion Award, Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus	HKUST, HK
Sep 20	CCMS PhD Scholarship, Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK	Lahore, PK
Sep 20	13 Participant , Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative	Islamabad, PK
Apr 20	Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition	Islamabad, PK
Apr 20	13 Participant, Case EPICA	Islamabad, PK
Apr 20	13 Participant , How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Oct 20	12 Participant , Punjab Youth Festival	Lahore, PK
Oct 20	11 Participant , Int'l Youth Conference and Festival	Islamabad, PK
Sep 20	11 Participant , Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival	Lahore, PK
Apr 20	11 Completion Award , Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Dec 20	11 Participant , National Drama Festival	Islamabad, PK
Dec 20	10 Instuctor of short Course, PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU	Islamabad, PK
Apr 20	Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan	Mansehra, PK
Apr 20	Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club	Islamabad, PK
Dec 20	08 Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU	Islamabad, PK

Academic Activities

RA-L	Referee Service, IEEE Robotics and Automation Letter	2022
TC	Referee Service, IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020, -21
ICRA	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2022, -21, -20
IROS	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2021,-20, -19, -18
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing		Spr 2020, Spr 2019,
		Spr 2018
CASE	Referee Service, IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering	2019
HKUST, H	Fall 2018	
HKUST, H	Spr 2017	

Skills_

Robotics and Computer Vision Ubuntu, ROS, PCL, Docker, Catkin, OpenCV, OpenGV, Ceres Solver, g2o, Libpointmatcher

Machine Learning / Deep Learning Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA

Programming Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX, FPGA, Verilog

Web mkdocs, Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL

Languages English, Urdu

Research Publication

Autonomous Mobile Robot Navigation using Adaptive Neuro Fuzzy Inference System Conference Paper

Muhammad Husnain Haider and Hub Ali and Abdullah Aman Khan and Hao Zheng and M. Usman Maqbool Bhutta and Shaban Usman and Pengpeng Zhi and Zhonglai Wang

May 2022

2022 International Conference On Innovations And Development Of Information Technologies And Robotics (IDITR), 2022

Why-So-Deep: Towards Boosting Previously Trained Models for Visual Place Recognition

Journal Paper

Jan 2022

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Yuxiang Sun, Darwin Lau and Ming Liu

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RA-L)/ICRA, 2022

Scale-Adaptive Pothole Detection and Tracking from 3-D Road Point Clouds

Conference Paper

Wu, Rigen and Fan, Jiahe and Guo, Libo and Qiao, Lei and Bhutta, M. Usman Maqbool and Hosking, Brett and Vityazev, Sergey and Fan, Rui

Aug 2021

2021 IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST), 2021

Loop-box: Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Mapping

Journal Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu and Ming Liu IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (**IF: 11+**)

Oct 2020

Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects for Industrial Automation

Conference Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Shoaib Aslam, Peng Yun, Jianhao JIAO and Ming Liu IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020)

Oct 2020

Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation

Conference Paper

Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Wang, Ming Liu and Rui Fan

Dec 2018

Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018)

PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM

Conference Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta* and Ming Liu

Jul 2018

Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award.

An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm

Conference Paper

M Usman Magbool Bhutta*, Hasan Mahmood, and Haroon Malik

Jan 2015

Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014). Efficient Reset Design Techniques

Qamar, Zoha, Bushra Yaseen, and Usman Maqbool

Journal Paper

Published in Science International Lahore

JULY 8, 2022

2015



Semi-Supervised Learning Approach for Smart Phone Glasses Defect Inspection

Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Yuan Wang, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,937, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

US Patent

Jan 2020

Automatic Surface Defect Detection System for Smart Phone Glass Based on Deep Learning

Yuan Wang, Jianhao Jiao, Peng Yun, Muhammad Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Xuebin Sun, Ming Liu U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 62/974,938, Filing Date 01/06/2020.

US Patent

Jan 2020

References

Prof Darwin Lau

Associate Professor · Director of C3 Robotics Lab (C3RL), Department of Mechanical and Automation Engineering, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, HK. (+852) 3943 8523

Postdoc Supervisor

darwinlau@cuhk.edu.hk

Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma

Senior Researcher · ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland (+41) (0) 44 633-8803

Exchange Co-Supervisor

cesarcadena.lerma@gmail.com

Prof Ming Liu

Associate Professor · Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB), Department of Electronic and Computer Enginneering, HKUST, HK.

Ph.D. Supervisor

eelium@ust.hk

(+852) 2358 7058